hello everyone jennifer maker here it's
a beautiful day to make amazing balloon
bouquets
just like this one right here so these
fun balloon projects have been blowing
up lately i've seen them made as
birthday gifts on display at parties as
centerpieces and even given out as
promotional items for businesses yes
really they make a big impact with a big
beautiful clear balloon and there are so
many decorations that you can put inside
i think that they're really fun
and everyone always wants to know the
secret of how to get those balloons
inside the big one and i'm going to
share my best tips so you can make these
beautiful bouquets yourself
using the right materials and some
special techniques we will take the
mystery out of them for you so you can
mystify your friends and family i'll
also share some balloon specific vinyl
designs like this one that you can use
to customize your balloon bouquet for
every event or gift so let's head on
over to my craft table and we will get
started
[Music]
so let's first talk about the balloons
that you need for this project it is
really important to use a big balloon to
get the right look for this bouquet so i
tried out a few different options and
during testing i looked at different
balloon strength how well they worked
with vinyl and how easy it was to work
with in general my favorite hands down
is definitely the 24 inch bobo balloon
vinyl sticks really well to the clear
surface and it's super strong so you can
shape it a bit and decorate it with
confidence and because the bobo balloon
is so strong it does take some
preparation to blow up so i'm going to
share those tips in this tutorial as
well but don't worry i will walk you
through it all and when you order these
balloons several usually come in the
pack that is perfect for learning a new
skill because you should always plan a
test run before you make your finished
project i always do at least so set
aside some time to get familiar with
these bobo balloons if you haven't used
them before and you will have awesome
results
and i should note that balloon projects
always come with some allergy concerns
because many do use latex
unfortunately the bobo balloon does
contain latex so please don't use this
project if you're allergic also check
that it's safe to give someone a gift
with latex before you actually do it for
example i wouldn't want to give this to
my niece who has a latex allergy if you
can't use latex balloons for any reason
vinyl designs also stick to mylar blends
which come in lots of fun shapes all
right so if latex is okay for your
project i found that these small
balloons here
are easy to get into the bobo if you
follow my steps i blew them up to about
five inches or so and i place four to
six of them in the big balloon i'll also
show you a little hack in the tutorial
for using extras of these small balloons
too
and this confetti here
lossl looks really awesome in the
balloon i have it in this one right here
you can get really creative with what
you put inside the balloon once you get
the basic process down
this balloon hand pump will become your
best friend while making balloon
bouquets it is strong enough to blow up
the big bobo balloon which does take a
lot of pumps a hand pump is definitely
required for this project you will not
be able to blow up these balloons all by
yourself even if you're a deep sea diver
and don't fill up some of the balloons
with helium and others with the pump
because then they will deflate at
different times and that won't look so
great so assembling the bouquet and base
takes a few items this four and a half
inch round gift box was perfect for the
project as i pictured it in my head but
you can certainly use a different
container just make sure it's sturdy
enough to hot glue the balloon stick
inside the balloon stick looks like this
the stick and the attached cup are what
keeps the big balloon in place you can
cut the stick to whatever height you
want and i'll explain that in the
tutorial
so filling and decorating the gift box
is almost as much fun as filling the
balloon you can use a combination of
tissue paper real or crafted flowers
candy even a plush animal some of my
projects from my dollar tree qriket
projects tutorial would fit perfectly
you can find them over at
jennifermaker.com dollartree cricut
projects
alright so i made my vinyl decals that
you see here on the balloons with my
cricut cutting machine
i use permanent adhesive vinyl in
various colors you can use your favorite
colors match a theme or use holographic
vinyl for some added sparkle
standard grip transfer tape works really
well for this project and i have a tip
for that as well
now since we're using adhesive vinyl
you'll also need your standard grip
machine mat a brayer a pair of scissors
and a weeding tool and i'll show you a
few tips on preparing your materials
that include a lint-free cloth super
useful
painters tape and a measuring tape too
so let me show you where you can get my
free designs for these balloons and then
we will get started
step one get my free balloon decal
designs
you can find all of these designs on my
blog go to jennifermaker.com
386 and look for libraries in the red
bar at the top
and then either click get a password if
you don't yet have one or click enter
the library
search the page for design number 386
and then click it to download a zip file
with an svg folder for cutting on a
cricut or another cutting machine
dxf files and printable pdfs for cutting
by hand
let me show you how to cut this design
on a cricut cutting machine
there are three design options in the
folder
one says happy birthday
another is for mother's day and the
third is a happy birthday with a
customizable name spot
i'll show you how to customize and cut a
decal using that last design
then you can use these steps to complete
the other designs or make something
entirely different
so first upload the spg cut file to
qriket design space
if you're unsure how to do this please
go to jennifermaker.com
svgs to learn how to unzip and upload
svg files
step 2 customize and cut the decal
here's what my customizable birthday
design looks like on my canvas
if you need to you can zoom out to see
the design by clicking on the minus sign
over on the lower left
this design is sized for the 24 inch
bobo balloon
so the decal is about nine inches wide
and seven and a half inches tall
if you're using a different balloon
resize it to fit by clicking and
dragging the designs resize icon right
here
or type a new dimension in the width
field in the top menu
either way make sure the lock icon is
closed to maintain the design's
proportions
if you need any help resizing svg in
qriket design space check out my
resizing guide over at jennifermaker.com
resize
svg
i designed these decals in a specific
way to make them easier to use on a
balloon
curved slippery surfaces take some
planning
see how the design is separated into
nine layers
we're going to apply each element to the
balloon individually instead of all at
once
i'll show you how to get everything
aligned so don't worry
now unless you have a friend named name
let's edit that text layer it's just a
placeholder
so select the design and click ungroup
at the top of the layers panel
now click on the word name to highlight
it in there
click its i icon right here to hide it
and now we have a space for a new name
click the text icon on the left of the
screen
a box with text highlighted in it will
appear on the canvas
now without clicking anything else type
in the name that you want
i will type in alexa
then click the box that says cricut sans
under font in the top menu to see your
font options
scroll through and click fonts to see
how your name looks in it until you find
one you like make sure your font choice
doesn't have a price next to it to avoid
a charge when you go to cut the design
i'm going to use the font called tingler
print which can be purchased from
fontbundles.net
but you can use the font that you like
the best
if you're using a long name don't worry
we can adjust the design
if you need any help filtering and
finding the best fonts check out my font
finder cheat sheet over at
jennifermaker.com
cricut fonts list
next drag the name into position under
the word birthday
change the color to match the word happy
if you want your colors to match that is
to do this just click on the colored
square in the top menu and select the
color that you want you can also resize
your name now if you'd like it bigger or
smaller
once your name is perfect look at the
stars on either side
if the new name takes up more or less
space than the name did before they
might be too close or too far from the
design
but it's an easy fix
click and drag each star closer to or
farther from the name until you're happy
if you make a mistake just click the
undo arrow in the top menu
remember we'll place the design element
separately so it doesn't have to be
perfect on the screen you can use these
same steps to adjust the happy mother's
day decal for different celebrations
to do this click ungroup and then hide
the mother's layer and replace it with
another word such as
father's
if you want the font to match i used a
font called beachwood which you can also
get from fontbundles.net
now beechwood is a script font which
means we want any connected letters to
cut as one piece and i'm happy to report
that cricut already knows this and will
auto weld them for us when we go to cut
it so there's no need to weld it
manually
so just resize and change the color to
match the other words remember the
design doesn't have to be perfect on the
screen you can position the flowers and
other decal pieces as needed on the
balloon it's really flexible
back on our happy birthday design it's
time to cut make sure you have the right
machine selected and click make it
if prompted click on matte and continue
if you're using the same colors as me
you should see three mats of different
colors on the prepare screen we're going
to cut each of the nine elements apart
before applying them to the balloon so
you may need to move them on the mats to
add some extra space for cutting them
apart with scissors
click on an element and drag it just
enough to cut between each with a pair
of scissors
here's what my elements look like on my
three mattes after spacing them out
click continue in the bottom right
and now we choose our material
we're using permanent adhesive for all
of the mats so set your material to
premium vinyl permanent glossy
i always like to change my pressure to
more for a cleaner cut
check remember these materials box to
save yourself some time
now place your first piece of vinyl
shiny side up on your machine mat and
use a brayer to make sure it's fully
adhered
check that your fine point blade is
clean and in clampy and then load the
mat into your machine
and press the flashing button to begin
cutting
when the cut is finished unload the mat
flip it over and roll it back to release
the vinyl repeat the same steps for the
other mats
step 3 prepare the decals
now let's get our decals ready so that
they're ready to go once the balloon is
blown up
cut the excess vinyl away from your
designs and separate the elements
with your weeding tool remove the excess
vinyl from the decals
making sure to get the letters centers
now cut a piece of transfer tape a bit
larger than the word birthday as we'll
be applying that piece first
remove the backing from the transfer
tape
fresh transfer tape is so sticky that it
will grab the balloon surface and risk
popping it
so here's a tip
stick the tape to a lint-free cloth
and peel it off to tone down on the
grabbiness of the transfer tape
now apply the transfer tape to your
birthday vinyl decal by holding the
transfer tape in the shape of a taco or
a u-shape and then put the bottom of
your taco onto the middle of your design
smooth the tape over the decal from the
center outward to minimize wrinkles and
bubbles
and burnish the decals front and back
with your scraper or a store loyalty
card
step 4 prepare the balloon and bouquet
materials
now let's get the base ready too
gather your gift box hot glue gun filler
balloon stick scissors tissue paper
and anything else you want to put in the
finished box
i'm going to get some ribbon for
decoration too
turn on your glue gun and let it heat up
so it's ready
don't let it get near your balloons once
they're blown up though that bobo is
strong but the plastic will pop if you
touch it with the glue guns hot metal
tip
i cut a piece of ribbon 39 inches long
and i tied it in a bow around the box
a dot of hot glue will keep the bow in
place at the front
feel free to play with the decorations
and items that you want to put in the
box to see how tall they'll be
you can use coffee filters or other
inexpensive paper as the bottom layer to
fill up any empty space and prop up
whatever you add to the box
then place the balloon stick in the box
and cut it so it sticks out above the
contents a bit
for mine i cut the stick to about 9
inches
remove the decorations and hot glue one
end of the stick into the center of the
box
and hold it in place while the glue
dries
reassemble the decorations in the box
making sure you don't jostle the stick
too much
if it falls over just glue it again
you can use hot glue to keep your filler
and other items in place too
[Music]
here's how mine looks but you can try
lots of different ideas
now we can blow up the balloons unplug
your glue gun just to be on the safe
side and you may want to remove any
jewelry and smooth your nails to avoid
snagging the balloon too
can you tell i don't want this balloon
to pop
so do you remember how i mentioned
preparing the big bobo balloon
here's what i found helped it reaches
blown up potential
hold the balloon in both hands and pull
it tightly in opposite directions
go around the entire perimeter of the
balloon
stretching it as you go do this several
times when you're done your balloon will
look a little wrinkly okay a lot wrinkly
this is what we want
i also added some air to the bobo and
released it right away a few times
doing this until it wasn't really
wrinkly made the plastic easier to
inflate
[Music]
and now for the magic inflating balloons
within a balloon
so pick the colors that you want to use
for the small balloons
secure one on the balloon pump but don't
inflate it
place the small balloon inside your
uninflated bobo balloon
pushing the main part of the small
balloon up inside the large area of the
bobo
and here's a tip if you're having
trouble wrangling both balloons and the
pump
bunching up or folding the bobo's neck
opening made it easier to get the small
balloon in place
this could take some practice so don't
worry
hold the opening of the bobo balloon
tightly around the end of the balloon
pump
to keep it in place while inflating the
small balloon inside of it
the small balloons take just four or
five pumps to inflate to about five
inches
once the small balloon is inflated hold
its end tightly and remove it from the
balloon pump
don't let any of the air escape or lose
the little balloon inside of the bobo
now tie the small balloon tightly and
let it go so it isn't completely inside
the bobo balloon
isn't that cool
so repeat for three to five more small
balloons
if you want to add confetti or other
non-sharp decorations to the bobo this
is the right time to do it
once you have a couple balloons blown up
inside the big one it will start getting
crowded and you may need to add some air
to the bobo balloon itself
add only enough air to give the small
balloons some room and allow space for
more balloons
if you're having trouble keeping the air
inside or you need to stretch your hands
give the balloon neck a few twists and
clip it closed with a binder clip or a
clothespin
that's also helpful when you're
preparing the next little balloon
and don't worry if some of the air
escapes while you're placing your next
balloon inside
your bobo balloon will expand with each
new balloon and you can add more air as
[Music]
needed once you have your small balloons
inside you can blow up the bobo balloon
i found a few tips to shape the bobo
for our design to look straight the bobo
balloon needs to be more of a circle
than an egg shape
since the balloon is so strong we can
shape it a bit while we're blowing up
here's how you do it
use the pump to blow up the bobo until
there are no more wrinkles
then remove the pump
hold the opening of the balloon closed
and carefully flip the balloon so the
top is touching your work surface
with a bit of downward pressure roll the
bobo's top to push the air more toward
the opening
this will help the top and bottom of the
balloon stretch into more of a circle
let a bit of air out and repeat the
rounding process
then fully inflate the balloon and check
that it's closer to a circle than an egg
and repeat until you're happy with the
shape
since the bobo is so strong i found that
i could keep adding air even after it
looked full
i had the best results when i blew up
the balloon to a circumference of
between 40 and 48 inches at the widest
part
hold the end of the boba balloon tightly
and remove the pump making sure you
don't let the air escape
twist the end several times before tying
it off and tie it as tightly as you can
for added security i used an uninflated
small balloon like a string and tied it
in a knot above the bobo's knot
now to prepare and add our decals i
tried a few different ways to apply the
decals nice and straight on the balloon
with mixed results
since everyone's balloon will be a
slightly different size and shape
getting everything perfect takes some
experimentation the bobo kind of has a
mind of its own so i tried a few ways to
keep it steady as usual painters tape is
the answer and i'll explain
so place your bobo on the work surface
making sure the center of one side is
facing up
you can use the side seams to check just
roll the balloon until one is on each
side and they're level
now cut a long piece of painters tape
and attach one end to the right side of
the balloon
cut another for the left and a third for
the top
check that the balloon is still centered
and attach the other ends of the tape to
the work surface
pulling them tightly so the balloon
can't move
it should look like mine
it kind of looks like how they hold a
hot air balloon in place with ropes
before it they lift it off doesn't it
we'll use painters tape again to create
a guideline for our first decal
look at your balloon from above and use
your best judgment to determine where
the horizontal center is
place a small square piece of tape on
the balloon in that spot
use your tape measure to check the
distance from the left seam to the piece
of tape and the distance from the right
seam to the tape
these distances should match
if they don't
carefully remove your tape and
reposition it accordingly
now it's really centered
repeat the measuring process to get the
vertical center too
measuring from the top seam and the knot
and adjust your tape square as needed
cut a six inch piece of tape and center
it on the small square
creating a longer reference line
look at your tape from above and make
sure it looks level
we don't want it slanting down to the
left or to the right
reposition it if you need to
step 5 apply the vinyl balloon bouquet
decal
now that our balloon center is marked
and it's secure we're ready to apply the
decals
i printed out a copy of my design to use
as a reference
but you can also just keep your cricut
design space canvas open to look at
so get your prepared birthday decal and
remove the paper backing from the vinyl
if your decal is still sticking to the
backing paper just replace the transfer
tape and burnish again
hold it just above the painters tape
aligning the decals and tapes centers
and here's an important tip
don't position the decal so that the
vinyl is on the tape if they overlap it
will be difficult to remove the painters
tape without moving your vinyl
make sure it looks level and then
lightly place the center of the decal
onto the balloon
allow the sides to fall flat against the
balloon but don't press anything down
just yet
step back and take a look at it the word
to see if it's positioned how you'd like
if not
no worries you can still remove the
decal and try again because you haven't
pressed down to adhere it yet
once you've got your decal where you
want it go ahead and press it down with
your fingers from the center outward
be gentle and try not to use your
fingernails because we don't want to
accidentally pop the balloon
press one letter down at a time making
sure to get them nice and smooth before
moving on to the next ladder
once you've pressed everything down
remove the painters tape and the
transfer tape
go slowly and make sure all the vinyl
letters stay attached to the balloon
if a letter starts to come up just push
it back down before moving on
place the transfer tape on the next
decal so it's ready to go
now since we know birthday is positioned
perfectly you can apply the word happy
above it using it as your reference with
the same technique
make sure you're happy with the
placement before pressing down
next apply the name that you've chosen
underneath the word birthday
the three words will be centered with
each other in the middle of the balloon
after you've applied the words add the
red sparkles and you can use your design
printout or canvas to help you with the
layout
and finally apply the stars
the small stars go on either side of the
name
the sets of stars go to the left and to
the right of the words happy birthday
with the large stars at the top on
either side of happy
and you did it you customized your
balloon with a fun decal
step 6 assemble the balloon bouquet
insert the bubble balloon's tied end
into the balloon cup slit and wrap it
around the base
if your end isn't long enough to wrap
around that's okay it should still stay
attached you can even add some tape or
rubber band if you want to make sure
it's attached really well
after you've attached the cup to the
balloon slide it onto the stick
and step back and check how everything
looks
be sure to admire your hard work
if you'd like you can add some finishing
touches with ribbon and
bows pretty impressive and not as
intimidating as they look right your
finished balloon bouquet is now ready
for a loved one or your next party and
now that you know all the secrets don't
you want to make a balloon bouquet for
every event i just love all of the
possibilities and i can't wait to see
what you come up with using this
tutorial
now
if you don't want to use up all of your
pretty tissue paper filling the box
because that box is pretty big coffee
filters make a great first layer
so that's a tip for you you can also use
a hot glue gun to keep everything in
place sticky glue dots are also helpful
if you need to secure something to your
balloon so make sure you have a variety
of different adhesives
and this is purely optional but i really
love how the ribbon pulls these bouquets
together i used a few different types as
you can see here
so balloon bouquets make great gifts for
all kinds of occasions you could make
one with flowers for mother's day or one
with candy for valentine's day that
would be really cool because you'd have
to pop it to get the candy or one with
fairy lights wrapped around it as a
centerpiece for a wedding you could even
add things like confetti flowers tissue
paper feathers or pom-poms inside your
bobo balloon instead of or in addition
to your small balloons
there are so many options for
customizing your bouquet and i'd love to
see what you come up with
so you can use my decals customize them
or start designing your own if you do
remember to break your design into
smaller elements to make applying them
easier it really really makes a
difference
all right now if you have any questions
about making these awesome balloon
bouquets that i didn't answer here in
this tutorial or anything else craft
related that i might be able to help you
with
let me know leave your question below
this video or
come ask over in our awesome qriket
crafters group at jennifermaker.com
cricketcrafters i love to help and i
love to see you make things
and that's it for today until next time
this is jennifer maker reminding you to
craft a life you love
[Music]